Guide to the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates Records 1828–2009 (bulk, 1912–2009) PR 370
New-York Historical Society
Gramercy Neighborhood Associates records
1828–2009 (bulk, 1912–2009)
New-York Historical Society
Gramercy Neighborhood Associates
PR 370
7.25 Linear feet in 11 boxes 2 oversize folders.
Organizational records, subject files, photographs, stereoviews, postcards, books, pamphlets, periodicals, and maps documenting the activities of the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, Inc., a group formed in 1912 (as the Gramercy Park Association) to stop the extension of Lexington Avenue through Gramercy Park, a private greenspace laid out in 1831. That battle won, the association subsequently engaged in a variety of community service and preservation projects, such as sponsoring the annual Gramercy Park Flower Show (1947–1994), and replacing the neighborhood's modern street lampposts with historic reproductions.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gramercy Neighborhood Associates in two parts: accession PPAC-2017-064 (received September 2017) and accession PPAC-2019-016 (received March 2019). Some of the items in Series VII were received on loan or deposit from the Trustees of Gramercy Park and/or the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates (then called the Gramercy Park Association) in 1949. For details, see the notes inside Box 11.
Arrangement
The collection organized in seven series:
Series I.
Organizational records, 1911–2009
Series II.
Subject files, 1831–2004
Series III.
Gramercy Park Flower Show, 1947–1994
Series IV.
Images, 1828–2000
Series V.
Print matter, 1894–2009
Series VI.
Maps, 1831–1953, undated
Series VII.
Material from the Trustees of Gramercy Park and Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, 1831–1956
Historical note
Gramercy Park, an approximately two-acre green space and surrounding neighborhood of the same name in Manhattan, was developed beginning in 1831 by attorney and politician Samuel B. Ruggles (1799–1881). Ruggles bought the land from a descendant of Peter Stuyvesant, drained the marsh formed by the "Krom Moerasje" brook (its name, in Dutch, which meant "crooked little swamp," was anglicized to "Gramercy"), and offered 66 building lots for sale. Lot holders enjoyed exclusive access to the park, which today remains one of only two private parks in New York City. Early residents included Valentine Mott (1785–1865), chief medical officer of the Union army during the Civil War and the founder of Bellevue Hospital; lawyer and diarist George Templeton Strong (1820–1875); and James Harper (1795–1869), publisher and 65th mayor of the City of New York (1844–1845).
Gramercy Park proper occupies a site between East 20th and East 21st Streets (a.k.a. Gramercy Park South and Gramercy Park North, respectively), midway between Third Avenue and Park Avenue South. A proposed bill to extend Lexington Avenue south through the park to join Irving Place prompted the formation in 1912 of the Gramercy Park Association (not to be confused with the older "Trustees of Gramercy Park," which first met in 1844 to oversee access to and maintenance of the park, or the "Gramercy Neighborhood Association," an anti-vice organization active circa 1913). The Gramercy Park Association successfully stopped the Lexington Avenue extension bill, thus maintaining the park's rectangular layout. That battle won, the association subsequently engaged in a variety of community service projects, such as the annual Gramercy Park Flower Show (1947–1994), and the replacement of the neighborhood's modern lampposts with historic reproductions of the bishop's crook design. In 1966, to qualify for tax exemption as a charitable organization under New York State law, the Gramercy Park Association incorporated as the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, Inc. (GNA). The GNA remains "dedicated to enhancing the aesthetic qualities and historic character of the Gramercy neighborhood and to developing a sense of community" through partnerships with area schools and local businesses. For information on current initiatives, visit gnaonline.org.
Related Materials
Researchers interested in the Gramercy Park Flower Show (see Series III) may also wish to consult the Horticultural Society of New York Records, 1811-circa 2010 (MS 3033).
Scope and Contents
The collection includes material generated and assembled by Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, Inc. (known before 1966 as the Gramercy Park Association), such as organizational records (1911–2009), subject files (1831–2004), documentation of the annual Gramercy Park Flower Show (1947–1994), images (1828–2000), books, pamphlets, and periodicals (1894–2009), and maps (1831–1953).
The organizational records include scattered meeting minutes, annual reports, committee, secretary, and treasurer reports, correspondence, by-laws, notices, invitations, fliers, and blank stationery. The subject files cover Gramercy Park proper, the surrounding neighborhood, its architecture, notable residents, and businesses. The Gramercy Park Flower Show, first held in 1947 and running annually as late as 1994, is represented by advertisements, brochures, internal memos and correspondence, invitations, newspaper clippings, and posters. The collection's images—consisting of photographs (many are copy prints), stereoviews, and postcards—capture Gramercy Park and other areas of Manhattan, mainly south of 23rd Street. Of particular note is a set of color photographs documenting cleanup efforts by Consolidated Edison after a steam pipe explosion released a cloud of asbestos over the neighborhood on August 19, 1989. Books and pamphlets about the park and neighborhood—most factual, but some fictional, like Victoria Thompson's Murder on Gramercy Park: A Gaslight Mystery (2001)—are supplemented by runs of local periodicals, namely the Gramercy Graphic (1954–1967), Gramercy Herald (1970–1985), Gramercy Neighborhood News (1988–1990), Gramercy: The Newsletter for the Gramercy Neighborhood (1991–1993), Gramercy Neighborhood Associates (1997), Gramercy Gazette (1997–2009), and the New York Chronicle (1987–1999), which carried contributions by longtime Gramercy Neighborhood Associates archivist Stephen Garmey in its pages. A series of original and reproduction maps of the neighborhood completes the collection.
Citizens' associations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Fiction.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- History.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Maps.; Gramercy Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Historic preservation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Horticultural exhibitions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Aerial photographs.; Annual reports.; Black-and-white photographs.; Books.; Color photographs.; Ephemera.; Maps.; Minutes (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Periodicals.; Postcards.; Stereographs.; Gramercy Neighborhood Associates -- Archives.
- Series I. Organizational records, 1911–2009
  Scope and Contents
  Scattered meeting minutes, annual reports, committee, secretary, and treasurer reports, correspondence, by-laws, notices, invitations, fliers, and other organizational records of Gramercy Neighborhood Associates. Note that materials dated before 1966 refer to the organization's original name: Gramercy Park Association.
  Arrangement
  Filed chronologically.
  - Record book, 1911–1926 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Includes constitution, meeting minutes, committee reports, secretary's reports, treasurer's reports, correspondence, meeting notices, etc.
  - Constitution (published) [10 folders], 1912–1962 (Box 1, Folder 1–10)
    • 1912 [2 copies]
    • 1917 [4 copies]
    • 1928
    • 1930
    • 1935
    • 1946 [2 copies]
    • 1949–50
    • 1953 [3 copies]
    • 1954
    • 1962 [4 copies]
  - Meeting notices, invitations, fliers, 1918–2009 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Christmas and Spring Messages, 1940–1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    • Christmas: 1940, circa 1940–1946 [3 copies], undated
    • Spring: undated
  - By-laws, corporate resolution, certificate of incorporation, tax exempt organization certificate, etc., 1966–2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports [8 folders], 1972–1979 (Box 2, Folder 3–10)
    • 1972
    • 1973 [3 copies]
    • 1974 [3 copies]
    • 1975 [3 copies]
    • 1976 [4 copies]
    • 1977 [2 copies]
    • 1978
    • 1979 [3 copies]
  - Archives, 1973–1974, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Information on the formation of the Gramercy Neighborhood Associates archives.
  - Publicity, circa 1970s–2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Stationery, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series II. Subject files, 1831–2004
  Material on Gramercy Park proper, the surrounding neighborhood, its architecture, notable residents, and businesses.
  - Ruggles documents, 1831, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Early deeds and correspondence of lawyer and politician Samuel B. Ruggles (1799–1881), the landholder who created Gramercy Park.
  - Trustees of Gramercy Park [2 folders], circa 1870–1966 (Box 4, Folder 2–3)
    Bills, receipts, and correspondence concerning the maintenance of and access to Gramercy Park.
  - Newspaper clippings [2 folders], 1881–1937, undated (Box 4, Folder 4–5)
  - Leopold Eidlitz (1823–1908), [1881–1976] (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Architect Leopold Eidlitz, with his partner Charles Otto Blesch, designed St. George's Episcopal Church (1846–1849) on Stuyvesant Square.
  - Cyrus W. Field (1819–1892), [1885] (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Photocopy of invitation from Cyrus W. Field to Henry L. Grant (1820–1894) to attend the eightieth birthday of Field's brother, David Dudley Field (1805–1894). The Field brothers lived on the site of No. 1 Lexington Avenue at the corner of Gramercy Park North.
  - John B. Pine's The Story of Gramercy Park, 1831–1921, 1919–1921 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    An advertisement and promotional material for John B. Pine's book, The Story of Gramercy Park, 1831–1921 (for a copy, see Box 8, Folder 24). Includes a 1919 letter from Alexander Duane to Pine informing him that he lacks a print or description of his great-great-grandfather's county seat on Gramercy Park.
  - Window gardens / flower boxes, 1919–1925 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Gramercy Park Hotel (52 Gramercy Park North), 1925–1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gramercy Park reminiscences, etc., circa 1929–1996, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Contains photocopies of
    • Recollections of Mrs. John B. Pine (Caroline Pryor), 24–25 Gramercy Park, New York City" (circa 1929)
    • Gramercy Park Centenary Celebration (1931)
    • Edith Wharton, "A Little Girl's New York," Harper's (March 1938)
    • Henry Hope Reed Jr., "Notes on Gramercy Park and its Periphery Prepared on the Occasion of the 74th Annual Meeting of the Municipal Art Society" (circa 1967)
    • Stephen Garmey, "Little-known Treasures on Irving Place" (November 1992)
    • Stephen Garmey, Foreword to Gramercy: Its Architectural Surroundings (Gramercy Neighborhood Associates, Inc., 1996)
    • Typescript "List of Illustrations" (undated)
    • "The Organ of Calvary Episcopal Church" (undated)
  - Calendars [3 folders], 1947, 2000–2001 (Box 3, Folder 2–4)
    • The Gramercy Park Calendar (1947)
    • Gramercy Park: A New York Neighborhood (2000) [3 copies]
    • Gramercy Gardens (2001) [2 copies]
  - MOVIETIME U.S.A., 1951 August 23 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Letter to Raymond Walburn of Beverly Hills, California, from Ronald Regan, as president of the Screen Actors Guild, discussing MOVIETIME U.S.A., a nationwide promotional tour campaign of Hollywood personalities. It is unclear why this letter is in the present collection, unless Gramercy Park was one of the locations of a celebrity visit.
  - Gramercy Graphic information, circa 1953–1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Promotional material and some correspondence regarding the Gramercy Graphic. (For a run of this periodical, 1954–1967, see Box 10, Folders 1–14.)
  - Vintage pamphlets & invitations of neighborhood locations, etc., 1953–2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    • Prince George Hotel (1953)
    • New York City Police Academy (circa 1954–1965)
    • Twenty-Third Street Association Membership Roster (1958)
    • National Arts Club [3 items] (1964, 1974, undated)
    • Church of the Epiphany, 375 Second Avenue [2 items] (1968, undated)
    • Theodore Roosevelt Birthplace [2 items] (1982, undated)
    • Peace Fountain (circa 1983)
    • Augustus Saint-Gaudens [2 items] (1985, 1990)
    • IFDA [International Furnishings and Design Association] (2004)
    • An Evening With George Templeton Strong (undated)
    • Autum Leaflet / Where to Dine / Where to Buy / Where to find needed Services (undated)
    • Friends of Gramercy (undated)
    • Parkside Hotel, 18 Gramercy Park South (undated)
    • Stanford White's New York (undated)
    • Stuyvesant Park Neighborhood Association (undated)
    • Connelly's [restaurant menu] (undated
    • Gramercy Park [restaurant menu] (undated)
  - Emory Lewis, "Gramercy Park Close-Up: A spring walking tour," CUE, 1964 April 25 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission, 1970, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Correspondence regarding the stable at 121 East 17th Street, and the H. Kauffman & Sons Saddlery Co. building at 139–141 East 24th Street, Manhattan, the latter since replaced by Baruch College.
  - STOP BIG MAC!, 1975 February 13 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Flier for "A Citizens' Meeting of Inquiry into McDonald's Move On Our Community," held in the Tiffany Room of the Gramercy Park Hotel.
  - Stephen Garmey's Gramercy Park: An Illustrated History of a New York Neighborhood, 1984–1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Promotional material for Stephen Garmey's book, Gramercy Park: An Illustrated History of a New York Neighborhood. (For a copy, see Box 8, Folder 10.)
  - Lampposts [2 folders], 1990–2006 (Box 3, Folder 12–13)
    Documentations of efforts by Gramercy Neighborhood Associates to replace the area's modern lampposts with historic reproductions.
  - Ludwig Bemelmans (1898–1962), 1998 July (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Ludwig Bemelmans, perhaps best remembered for creating the beloved children's book character "Madeline," was a longtime resident of Gramercy Park. He died in 1962 at the National Arts Club (15 Gramercy Park South).
  - Albinas Elskus (1926–2007), undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Stained glass artist Elskus designed windows for the Roman Catholic Church of the Epiphany, 375 Second Avenue.
- Series III. Gramercy Park Flower Show, 1947–1994
  Advertisements, brochures, internal memos and correspondence, invitations, newspaper clippings, and posters for the Gramercy Park Flower Show, held annually beginning in 1947 and running through, at least, 1994. Locations include the National Arts Club (15 Gramercy Park South) and the Gramercy Park Hotel (2 Lexington Avenue).
  - 1st annual flower show, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 2nd annual flower show, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 3rd annual flower show, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 4th annual flower show (theme: Pan-America), 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 5th annual flower show (theme: New York is a Symphony), 1951 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 6th annual flower show (theme: Mediterranean Cruise), 1952 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 7th annual flower show (theme: The Exotic East), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 8th annual flower show (theme: April Back Home), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 9th annual flower show (theme: Widening Horizons), 1955 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 10th annual flower show (theme: Flower Festival of Arts), 1956 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 11th annual flower show (theme: The Magic of Africa), 1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 12th annual flower show (theme: America the Beautiful), 1958 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 13th annual flower show (theme: Hudson River Saga), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 14th annual flower show (theme: The Seven Seas), 1960 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - 15th annual flower show (theme: Flower Carnival), 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 16th annual flower show (theme: Alice in Wonderland), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 17th annual flower show (theme: Broadway), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - 17th annual flower show (theme: Broadway), 1963 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 1)
  - 18th annual flower show (theme: Here's Flowers for You) [inspired by Shakespeare], 1964 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - 19th annual flower show (theme: Reaching for the Stars), 1965 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - 20th annual flower show (theme: Flashback), 1966 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - 21st annual flower show (theme: Mother Goose Rides Again), 1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - 22nd annual flower show (theme: Garden of Jewels), 1968 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - 23rd annual flower show (theme: Live with Flowers), 1969 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - 24th annual flower show (theme: Festivals—U.S.A.), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - 28th annual flower show (theme: Fashions and Flowers), 1974 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 1)
  - 30th annual flower show (theme: A Salute to the Bicentennial), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - 30th annual flower show (theme: A Salute to the Bicentennial), 1976 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 1)
  - 35th annual flower show (theme: Doorways on the Park in Celebration of the 150th Anniversary of Gramercy Park), 1981 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - 41st annual flower show (theme: The Language of Flowers), 1987 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - 42nd annual flower show (theme: Time and Again) [date discrepancy as in original], 1989 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - 43rd annual flower show (theme: On the Avenue—Fifth Avenue), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - 44th annual flower show (theme: Ellis Island—Isle of Hope), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - 44th annual flower show (theme: Ellis Island—Isle of Hope), 1991 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 1)
  - 45th annual flower show (theme: You're the Top) [inspired by Cole Porter], 1992 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - 45th annual flower show (theme: You're the Top) [inspired by Cole Porter], 1992 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 1)
  - 46th annual flower show (theme: Rock Stars) [date discrepancy as in original], 1994 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Flower show fact sheets and stationery, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Series IV. Images, 1828–2000
  Photographs, prints, stereoviews, and postcards of Gramercy Park, its surrounding neighborhood, and other areas of Manhattan, mostly south of 23rd Street. Many images are reproductions or copy prints.
  - Subseries IV.A. Photographs and prints, 1828–2000
    Filed geographically, starting with Gramercy Park and the streets fronting it (Gramercy Park North, South, East, and West), followed by numbered Manhattan streets (running east-west), numbered and named Manhattan avenues (running north-south), squares, aerial views, unidentified locations, and people. The handwritten page numbers on some images refer to Stephen Garmey's Gramercy Park: An Illustrated History of a New York Neighborhood (1984). For a copy of the book, see Box 8, Folder 10.
    - Gramercy Park, circa 1905–2000 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Views of Gramercy Park proper, including its paths, plantings, statuary, fountains, and fence.
    - Gramercy Park [oversize], 1946, 1948 (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 2)
      Artistic depictions of Gramercy Park from The Saturday Evening Post, October 12, 1946 and January 3, 1948.
    - Gramercy Park asbestos steam explosion cleanup, 1989 August-October (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Color photographs (including aerial views) documenting the cleanup efforts by Consolidated Edison following a steam pipe explosion outside 32 Gramercy Park South (southwest corner of Third Avenue and East 20th Street) that killed three people, injured twenty-four, and released a cloud of asbestos over the neighborhood on August 19, 1989.
    - Gramercy Park North (a.k.a. East 21st Street), 1898–1927 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Views of the buildings fronting Gramercy Park North (a.k.a. East 21st Street), including the residence of architect Stanford White (121 East 21st Street).
    - Gramercy Park South (a.k.a. East 20th Street), 1876–2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Views of the buildings fronting Gramercy Park South, including the National Arts Club (15 Gramercy Park South) and The Players (16 Gramercy Park South).
    - Gramercy Park East, 1863–1992 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Views of the Gramercy Park House (hotel), which occupied the sites of the apartment houses at nos. 34 and 36 Gramercy Park East, which are also represented
    - Gramercy Park West, 1846–1959 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Views of buildings and architectural details on Gramercy Park West, including stills from the film "Happy Anniversary" (1959), starring David Niven and Mitzi Gaynor, shot at 1 Gramercy Park West.
    - East 14th Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Nineteenth-century view of the north side of East 14th Street at Irving Place, showing the Steinway & Sons building and the Academy of Music.
    - East 15th Street, 1893, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Views of Samuel B. Ruggles's former stable (103 East 15th Street), Brewer's Exchange [or Century Association Building] (109 East 15th Street), and the New-York Dispensary for Women and Children (corner Livingston Place).
    - East 17th Street, circa 1870, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Views of the Everett House (northwest corner of Fourth Avenue); a former stable (121 East 17th Street); and Joe King's German American Rathskeller [Scheffel Hall] (141–145 East 17th Street, a.k.a. 190 Third Avenue).
    - East 19th Street, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Views of nos. 129 and 146 East 19th Street, the latter the residence of artist George W. Bellows (1882–1925).
    - East 21st Street, 1930s, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 11)
      Views of nos. 21 (color) and 147–159 East 21st Street.
    - East 22nd Street, circa 1864 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Twenty-second Street, looking east from Broadway, circa 1864, showing th south tower of Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church and the spire of St. Paul's Methodist Church at the corner of Fourth Avenue.
    - East 23rd Street, circa 1894–1905 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Views of the National Academy of Design (northwest corner of East 23rd Street and Fourth Avenue) and East 23rd Street trolleys at Fourth Avenue.
    - West 53rd Street, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      View of Mount Olivet Baptist Church, 161 West 53rd Street.
    - First Avenue, circa 1944, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Views of the intersection of First Avenue and East 20th Street (showing gas tank) and Stuyvesant Town-Peter Cooper Village under construction (aerial).
    - Second Avenue, circa 1964 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      Views of Church of the Epiphany (Roman Catholic), 373 Second Avenue at East 22nd Street, taken after the fire that destroyed it on December 20, 1963.
    - Second Avenue [oversize], undated (Folder Oversize 1, Enclosure 3)
      View of the Society for the Lying-In Hospital (305 Second Avenue).
    - Third Avenue, 1865–circa 1962 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Views of the Seventh Regiment Armory (Third Avenue between East 6th and 7th Streets), Scheffel Hall interiors (190 Third Avenue), Chancellor Walworth Lodge (northwest corner of Third Avenue and East 20th Street), and Third Avenue looking north and south from East 22nd Street.
    - Irving Place, circa 1880–1976 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      Views of the Consolidated Edison Building (4 Irving Place); cornerstone ceremonies for Washington Irving High School; the so-called Washington Irving House (4 Irving Place); east and west sides of Irving Place between East 17th Street and Gramercy Park South.
    - Lexington Avenue, circa 1860s–1920s (Box 6, Folder 19)
      Views of Peter Cooper House (9 Lexington Avenue); 11 Lexington Avenue; and the Free Academy (Lexington Avenue at East 23rd Street).
    - Fourth Avenue (Park Avenue South), circa 1863–1949 (Box 6, Folder 20)